<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes out of Holland: concerning Barnevelt and his fellow-prisoners their conspiracy against their natiue country, with the enemies thereof the oration and propositions made in their behalfe vnto the Generall States of the vnited Prouinces at the Hague, by the ambassadors of the French king. With their answere therevnto, largely and truely set downe: and certaine execrable articles and opinions, propounded by Adrian du Bourg, at the end. VVherevnto is adioyned a discourse, wherein the Duke D'Espernons revolt and pernicious deseignes are truely displayed, and reprehended, by one of his friends.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 930:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes out of Holland: concerning Barnevelt and his fellow-prisoners their conspiracy against their natiue country, with the enemies thereof the oration and propositions made in their behalfe vnto the Generall States of the vnited Prouinces at the Hague, by the ambassadors of the French king. With their answere therevnto, largely and truely set downe: and certaine execrable articles and opinions, propounded by Adrian du Bourg, at the end. VVherevnto is adioyned a discourse, wherein the Duke D'Espernons revolt and pernicious deseignes are truely displayed, and reprehended, by one of his friends.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathanael Newbery, and are to bee sould at his shop vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley at the signe of the Star,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oldenbarnevelt, Johan van, 1547-1619.</term>
               <term>Epernon, Jean-Louis de Nogaret de La Valette, --  duc d', 1554-1642.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Twelve Years' Truce, 1609-1621 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Newes out of</hi> Holland: Concerning Barnevelt and his fellow-Priſoners their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt their Natiue Country, with the Enemies thereof: THE Oration and Propoſitions made in their behalfe vnto the Generall <hi>States</hi> of the vnited Prouinces at the HAGVE, by the <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> KING. WITH Their Anſwere therevnto, largely and truely ſet downe: And certaine Execrable Articles and Opinions, propounded by <hi>Adrian du Bourg,</hi> at the end. VVherevnto is adioyned a Diſcourſe, wherein the Duke <hi>D'Eſpernons</hi> revolt and pernicious deſeignes are truely diſplayed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, by one of his Friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhop vnder S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley at the ſigne of the Star. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:2"/>
            <head>THE ORATION AND PROPOSITIONS made on <hi>Barnavelt's</hi> and his fellow-Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners behalfe, by the <hi>French</hi> Kings <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> to the generall Eſtates of the vnited Prouinces of HOLLAND, &amp;c. at the preſenting of his Maieſties Letters vnto the ſaid Eſtates.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lords, the King our Maſter commanded vs, to recommend vnto you the ſame which we haue heretofore at other times motioned, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good, and peace of your eſtate: although it hath not bin conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red according to the worthineſſe of the merit of his alliance and amitie: but in the preſent ſtate of your affaires, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie will not ceaſe to witneſſe vnto you, that he hath no leſſe care thereof, then of the peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of his owne Kingdome.</p>
            <p>We will therefore proceede to exhort you, to continue ſtedfaſt in the vnion of your Prouinces, as the principall foundation of your eſtate, and to be
<pb facs="tcp:13800:3"/>carefull, that the changing of Magiſtrates and Counſellors, which hath bin made in diuers of your Townes, doe not breede enmities and diſſentions among your Citizens, inſtead of ceaſing them; for that, all mutations and changes of Magiſtrates, Lawes, and policies are dangerous to publique go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernements, if they be not made vpon great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and ſo profitable for the Commons, that no man may haue cauſe to diſlike them: Therefore it is requiſite for you to take order, that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, by their good and iuſt proceedings and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, may obtaine and deſerue the good-will of the people; and ſhew themſelues ſo modeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that are diſmiſſed, that the inconſtant multitude may haue no occaſion to repine at ſuch alteration; and that thoſe that haue bin depoſed from their charges, ſhould patiently endure and beare that alteration, as being made for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of the ſtate.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sinode</hi> which you haue cauſed to be aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, puts vs in good hope that it will be a meanes to procure peace and concord touching thoſe points of Religion, which haue bred trouble and ſchiſme in theſe Prouinces among you: To make it effectuall and fruitfull, it is requiſite that it ſhould be free, and ſecure for all thoſe that ſhall therein aſſemble together, and that the points in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie ſhould be examined and diſputed of, without paſſion, or for any other conſideration, then onely for the honour of God, and the peace of mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
            <p>And certainely, whoſoeuer taketh vpon him to
<pb facs="tcp:13800:3"/>interpret, or attaine vnto thoſe high miſteries and treaſures of diuine wiſedome, without great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſubmiſſion; ſhall finde himſelfe as farre off from them, as he thinketh he approacheth neere vnto them.</p>
            <p>We are likewiſe to tell you ſomewhat from the King, touching your Priſoners, and to ſhew you, how much it concerneth the honour and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your affaires, and generally the peace of your Prouinces, and concord among your ſubiects, to adminiſter vnto them good and ſpeedy Iuſtice. They are accuſed of the moſt inorme and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble crimes that can be, as of Treaſon againſt their natiue Countrey, ſecret intelligence with your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and for hauing expoſed your Townes vnto the danger of pillage, and effuſion of blood.</p>
            <p>If they be culpable of theſe diſloyalties, the King our Maſter giueth you counſell and aduiſe to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the rigour of your Lawes againſt them. But as thoſe crimes are grieuous, and worthy of moſt great puniſhment; ſo they haue beene reduced to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine points, whereunto good and wiſe Princes, and well gouerned common-wealths would not ſtretch them.</p>
            <p>To the contrary, diuers Princes haue ſhewed themſelues ready to pardon, euen ſuch enterpriſes as haue bin done againſt their owne perſons: and the freeſt Common-wealths, alwaies vſed to ſpare the blood of their Citizens; and that in the greateſt malefactors; it being one of the principalleſt ſignes of liberty and freedome, not eaſily or lightly to touch the life of Citizens.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:4"/>
            <p>Therefore the crime of Treaſon ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and vnderſtood in her proper tearmes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out drawing it by conſequences and inductions to other actions which are not of the ſame quality. The contentions which oftentimes ariſe and are made in the management of affaires, the iealouſies of power and authority, and ambition which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies drawes and driues men to enterpriſe and take more vpon them then they ſhould, are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary euils in all ſtates; whereby many inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and miſchiefes enſew. Neuertheleſſe, they were neuer eſteemed nor held to be treaſon againſt the State, becauſe crimes and offences are iudged by the will and intent, and not by the euent.</p>
            <p>We doubt not, my Lords, but that in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrities and wiſedomes you make diſtinction as you ſhould, of the faith and actions whereof men are accuſed; queſtion being made of the liues of your officers &amp; ſubiects placed in authority, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is the auncienteſt Counſellor of your ſtate, which is <hi>Monſieur Barneuelt,</hi> ſo much commended for the good and notable ſeruices by him done for theſe countries, whereof the Princes and States and allies vnto the ſame are witneſſes, that it is hardly to be thought or beleeued, that he ſhould haue conſpired treaſon againſt his natiue Countrie, for the which you your ſelues know hee hath taken ſo great paines: neuertheleſſe ſeeing he is called in queſtion by order of Law, it importeth the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of your eſtate, that the truth ſhould be known; which to doe, you ought both for him, and the reſt alſo to appoint Iudges that are neither ſuſpected
<pb facs="tcp:13800:4"/>nor paſſionate, that iudge according to the Lawes of the Countrey, vpon cleere and euident proofes, as equitie requireth, and not vpon coniectures and preſumptions, which oftentimes deceiue Iudges; becauſe there are many things that are apparant and very likely, which neuertheleſſe are not true; and others that are true, and yet haue no likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: and ſo by moderate and vpright Iudgement, you ſhall manifeſt vnto the world, that you are worthy of the poſſeſſion and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this eſtate, to the gouernement whereof God hath called you.</p>
            <p>The counſell which the King giueth you, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Priſoners, is, not to vſe rigour againſt them; but rather fauour and clemency, as moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, and fit and conuenient to win the hearts of the people, &amp; to make them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. It is the ſecurity of States, ſuch as yours is, to revnite your ſubiects which are diuided, and to molefie and appeaſe the diſlikes and bitterneſſe, which is among them; wherevnto we haue ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge to adde his Maieſties requeſt and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, in reſpect of the intereſt which he hath in the preſeruation of your State, and his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the great ſeruices, which this Priſoner hath done for you; as alſo of the affection; which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bare to the maintenance of the alliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>France</hi> and this State, ſo notable actions and teſtimonies of his loyaltie and fidelity, that they ſeeme to exclude all ſuſpition of treaſon and diſloyaltie; and whereof as yet, his Maieſty can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:13800:5"/>hold or thinke him to be culpable, vntill by euident proofes you make the crime manifeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
            <p>Now after ſo many good aduiſes, which are on the Kings behalfe propounded vnto you, if you, for your parts, rather chuſe a rigorous courſe, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie ſhall haue ſufficient glory and ſatisfaction, to haue, like a true friend and allie, giuen you whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſound counſels, whereof the vſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent will be as happy and profitable for your State, as the contrary is hurtfull and dangerous: And his Maieſtie cannot chuſe but be much offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the ſmall reſpect which you ſtill make of his counſels, requeſts, and amitie, which thereby may procure as much ſlackneſſe, as in times paſt you haue found promptneſſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourableneſſe in your neede. In the <hi>Hague,</hi> preſented to the States.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>de Thumerie,</hi> and, <hi>du Morier.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:5"/>
            <head>The generall <hi>States</hi> anſwere to the Propoſitions, made vnto them by the French KINGS Ambaſſadors.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He STATES generall of the vnited Prouinces, hauing in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen aſſembly, heard, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately pervſed the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Meſsieurs do Boiſsiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>du Morier,</hi> Ambaſſadors of the moſt chriſtian King of <hi>France,</hi> deliuered by word of mouth the 12 of this month, and the next day in writing, by vertue of their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Credit, bearing date the 28. of <hi>Nouember.</hi> ſignifie and declare, that as they haue had nothing in more ſingular recommendation, then by the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of their actions and gouernments, to giue all good meanes and occaſions vnto his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> to moue him to continue his royall fauours and aides (following the example of the late King, of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall memory &amp; incomparable wiſdome) vnto them, for the good and maintenance of their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: to the which end alſo, they haue alwayes carefully, in their need, ſought for and imbraced his wholeſome counſels, aduiſes, and fauours, againſt the threatnings, deuiſes and powers of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for the which they are oblieged to giue and yeeld all kinde of thankes and gratefulnes vnto his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and kingdome: So they are exceedingly much grieued, to perceiue themſelues to be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and taxed, not to haue reſolued vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:13800:6"/>affaires done for them vpon occaſion of theſe laſt motions, touching the good of this <hi>State,</hi> according to the merit of his alliance and amitie, becauſe they cannot conceiue wherevpon this complaint of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhould be grounded; in regard that they haue alwaies had a ſpeciall care, moſt exactly to obſerue and keepe all the points, &amp; Articles of Couenants, which they haue had the honour to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and renewed with his Maieſtie, not once neglecting any clauſe thereof, whereby the leaſt cauſe or occaſion of diſcontentment, or iealouſie might grow or ariſe; and therefore the ſaid <hi>States,</hi> aſſure themſelues, that continuing the ſame courſe for the ſecuritie of their ſtate, which hitherto they haue carefully held and obſerued, in the ſtrict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and confederation wherewith the two Kings conſequently haue vouchſafed to honour him, his maieſtie will not at this preſent make any other conſtruction of their wills, and preſent carriages, then that which is requiſite to be made of a ſtate which is moſt thankefull for, and memoratiue of, his fauours and benefits, and no leſſe deſirous to ſhew the continuance of the moſt ſtrict bond there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in all reſpects which ſhall be thought or found to be profitable for the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, and conuenient for their owne ſecuritie.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe the ſaid ſtates, receiue and accept of, (as a moſt great fauour) the good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſells which it pleaſeth his Maieſtie to giue them, in this preſent eſtate wherein their affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res now ſtand, exhorting them to remaine firme and conſtant in the vnion of their prouinces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13800:6"/>they are altogether conformable to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; for they haue alwaies had the ſame deſire and deſigne, ſpecially to be carefull of the meanes to preſerue and defend their ſtate againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to vſe their friends and Allies worthily, according to their quallities and degrees.</p>
            <p>They alſo ſay that they haue not without great &amp; good conſideration beene moued to change cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of their Magiſtrates, in ſome of their Townes: whereof it may be, the report hath beene other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpread abroad, then the caſe requireth, ſeeing that the remedy was moſt neceſſary &amp; eaſie being wiſely and moderately applyed, without any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or danger of bloud-ſhedding, in ſuch manner that publique authority, vnion by peace, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance againſt diſorders are entirely eſtabliſhed, which certaine ambitious &amp; factious ſpirits would haue much altered, not without great danger, (if longer forbearance &amp; patience had beene vſed) to ouerthrow and deſtroy all the ſtate, and to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſolation of good men, and to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his Maieſtie, &amp; the good of his kingdome.</p>
            <p>Beſides that, they haue onely made a neceſſary change of ſome certaine perſons, not once thereby touching or altering the lawes, rights or pollicies of their Townes; neither haue they had any other intent or meaning in their elections of new Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, then onely to ceaſe the great partialities that haue crept in among them, by the practiſe of factious perſons, which in thoſe Townes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies proceeded ſo farre as to erect Alter againſt Alter: and in the ſame changes they haue placed
<pb facs="tcp:13800:7"/>none but ſuch perſons as are well quallified, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and affected to their Countrie, who without doubt, by their vpright and iuſt behauiour, know full well how to procure and get the good-will of the people, and to preſerue and defend the <hi>State</hi> from all violent alterations or motions; and that in many Townes the proofe of this lenitie alreadie appeareth, in that the order which hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effabliſhed for the protection and defence of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, againſt the firſt oppreſſion, is already nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſing, whereby all the members of this <hi>State</hi> conſpire and conſent together to caſt off and abandon their bad motions, and to raunge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnder lawfull obedience, by voluntarie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of their ſuperiours: And that if this proceeding of their factious ſubiects had drawne them vnto any greatextreamity, they would hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haue relied vpon the ordinary good will of his Maieſtie, for their ſupport and meanes, which might haue failed them, by their power to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed thoſe confuſions, which by the mercie and goodneſſe of God they did in time preuent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble or extraordinary charge to their allies.</p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Sinode,</hi> which hath beene called and aſſembled together in theſe Prouinces, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies certainely beleeued, that therby ſome means of peace and concord concerning, thoſe points of religion which haue bin the cauſe to adminiſter trouble in the Churches of ſome of their <hi>Prouinces,</hi> would be found, eſteeming it the moſt meet, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and lawfull meanes thereunto, vſed in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue Church, euen in the time of the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13800:7"/>But what meanes ſoeuer they haue heretofore vſed to obtaine and publiſh that conuocation, it was neuer till now in their power to attaine to that holy and wholeſome remedie, to rule and ſtop the differences in their firſt birth: And his <hi>Maieſty</hi> may well call to minde and remember, if it pleaſeth him, the intreaties and humble motions diuers times made by them vnto him, to be ayded and aſſiſted in this good worke, by the aſſiſtance of ſome of his ſubiects, choſen out of the reformed Churches in his Realme; but were croſſed and put off by them, with a ſmall number of perſons, who contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all reaſon and order of gouernement, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting their vocation, outwardly made the iuſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the ſaid <hi>States</hi> vnfruitfull: but now neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe that by the goodneſſe of God, and the moſt wiſe and reſolute conduction and dexterity of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> they haue aſſured their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſtate from preſent danger, they thought it not conuenient to neglect the care which they ought to haue of the Spirituall: To the which end, the <hi>Sinode</hi> was freely opened, and began to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Moneth of <hi>Nouember</hi> laſt, as they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with this onely preſcription and clauſe, not to ſeeke any other thing thereby, then the honour of God, and the peace of mens conſciences, in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his word, wherein there is found and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſo great a number of excellent perſons, both for pietie and vprightneſſe, choſen and appointed thereunto by their ſuperiours, that the <hi>States</hi> haue good cauſe to hope well of their labours; and that alſo, by Gods holy grace, the euent will teſtifie their iuſt and ſincere intentions, to the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:13800:8"/>of his Maieſtie, the good and peace of their common-wealth, and the confuſion of the authors of this faction.</p>
            <p>Further the ſaid State alſo eſteeme, weigh, and thinke very well of the reaſons and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons formerly ſet downe by the ſaid Lords Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, in fauour of the Priſoners, to adminiſter vnto them good and ſpeedie Iuſtice, and to vſe them fauourably, if they haue not conſpired the ruine of their State, with their enemyes: but for that the ſaid <hi>States</hi> haue beene continually buſied about ſetling the neceſſary ſecuritie of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, which had been greatly ſhaken by the violent proceedings of ſuch as aſpired to nouelties, by alteration of Religion, Iuſtice, and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of all polliticke orders: and that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this conſpiracie grew ſo great, that nothing was exempted from the infection thereof, they thought it not conuenient to run headlong vpon ſuch a proceſſe of ſo great importance, &amp; that firſt it was moſt fit ſeuerally to gather and collect all ſuch euidences as might tend vnto, and concerne the ſame, for their full inſtruction therein, clearely to make knowne and manifeſt the grounds and depth of the cauſe, and that ſuch delay could not be any wayes hurtfull or preiudiciall to the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minells, if they preſumed to haue any aduantage to iuſtifie their innocency. Notwithſtanding, there hath not therein bin any loſſe of time, but things haue bin done orderly and diligently, &amp; haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proceeded ſo farre, that they are perſwaded that iudgement ſhall not long be deferred, and ſuch without doubt, that at the publication thereof, all
<pb facs="tcp:13800:8"/>their allies, which affect the proſperity of this State, and ſpecially his Maieſtie, who is a iuſt and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, will commend their vpright dealing, when they ſhall be better informed of the ſtate of the conſpiracie.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, they deſire the ſaid Lords <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> to aſſure his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> from them, that they will encline themſelues ſo much to clemencie and fauour (wherevnto they, and the condition of their gouernment are naturally addicted) as equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, iuſtice, and the preſeruation of their State, may in any wiſe permit them: Hoping that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> (in regard of the cauſe) will not be perſwaded to prefer the important and ill-grounded ſolicitations of certaine particular criminels, or of their fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, before the generall intereſt of the dignitie and worthines of this Common-wealth; but to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary perſwade themſelues that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> will finde it more expedient for his ſeruice, &amp; the good of the ſaid Prouinces, to referre the ſame to the ſaid <hi>States</hi> gouernment and iudgement, which they will take paines to conclude and finiſh, with ſo much equitie and clemencie among themſelues, that the obedience of their ſubiects ſhall by their authority be confirmed, and with ſo great wiſdome &amp; reſpect of their allies, that his Maieſtie ſhall haue occaſion to content himſelfe with the duty which they will ſhew for the obſeruation and maintaining of his alliance with them, whereof they will truly yeeld him ſatisfaction.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen in the</hi> Hague <hi>at the generall aſſembly of the ſaid States.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Seauen</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles_of_faith">
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:9"/>
            <head>Seauen ARTICLES propounded by <hi>Adrian du Bourg.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>THat Originall-ſinne, is no ſinne, but an occaſion of Sinne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the great Mercy of God, is the onely cauſe of mans good, and that hee hath power to accept or refuſe it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That Faith, by the vertue of Gods great mercy, is the proper worke of man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That Gods prouidence is ſuch, that it foreſeeth all things, but worketh not in men particularly, whom he leaueth to their free-will.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That the faithfull or beleeuing Children of God, in this life, may perfectly accompliſh Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, although they doe them not.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>That the Children of God may fall from his grace and ſauing mercie, and ſo be damned.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 <hi>That the originall cauſe of Iuſtification before God, is the paſsion of Chriſt, but the workes of Obedience are the firſt originall cauſe of this Iuſtification.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:9"/>
            <head>The Duke <hi>D'Eſpernons</hi> reuolt and pernicious Deſignes, truely diſplayed <hi>and reprehended by one of his Friends.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true, and a common ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, my Lord, that thoſe which vſe to play, before they begin, ſhould be ſure to make a good match: it is the ſame aduiſe which you your ſelfe gaue to a turbulent ſpirit, that ſought the diſquietneſſe and ruine of <hi>France:</hi> an aduiſe which you ſuggeſted to be conuenient, by the knowledge that you had, that thoſe who ſeeke to ſet vpon and conſpire againſt their King, in the end come by the loſſe, I meane both of honour and life: And neuertheleſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting your owne inſtructions, and the examples which time hath produced; you are now fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame crymes, which formerly you abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and thereby become diſobedient and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Crimes, ſo much the more to be blamed, as they are committed by a perſon, who not onely ought to ſhun them, but to the contrary, is oblie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and bound by all manner of duties, to imploy both his body and goods againſt thoſe that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe
<pb facs="tcp:13800:10"/>them. I am ſo much grieued at your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that it moueth me boldly without difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to tell you, (being culpable as you are) that my aduiſe is, and inſtantly I beſeech you, to ſeeke out meanes to cure your malady, and to procure your owne ſafety, and therein to take my counſell, haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heretofore giuen you warning of your former actions, at the leaſt, I ſhall diſcharge my ſelfe of the duety which I owe vnto you, for the fauours I haue receiued at your hands, and I call heauen to witneſſe of my ſincerity; let me then intreat you, to peruſe theſe few lines, and ſuffer the truth therein by me ſet downe, to worke ſome remorſe of conſcience in you. Vpon what doe you thinke, I beſeech you, when you diſcharge your arrowes againſt the Kings Maieſty, and the peace of his eſtate? you that haue both the grace and honour to be one of the officers of his crowne, and haue as much charge and commoditie as any other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him? This is not the way, by waxing elder, to grow wiſer, but rather to counterfeit the Ape, which the older it groweth, the vnhappier it is. What? in a manner hauing one foote already in the graue, to damne his owne ſoule, and diſobay the King? and not onely to diſobay him, but to offend him, in the deareſt thing that he hath, and not onely to offend him therein, but to take vpon you to raiſe his Subiects to beare armes againſt him vnder light pretences, as the truth well ſheweth; I neither know, nor can conceiue, how a man eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be wiſe, whoſe beard is gray, and ſeemeth to be of a ſtayed iudgement, ſhould fall into ſo great
<pb facs="tcp:13800:10"/>folly; pardon me for ſpeaking ſo freely: A Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker muſt be lanched and cut away, your euill is no leſſe, and moſt dangerous. You are not ignorant, that Kings are the images of the liuing God, that their wils and commandements are Lawes to be ſpecially obſerued, and that no man can diſpenſe therewith, without being guilty of high treaſon, both diuine and humane, and yet, you haue not onely ventred to diſobey them, but alſo by a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of new interpretation, haue directly withſtood his commandements. The King thought your perſonall preſence to be neceſſary in <hi>Metz,</hi> and you thought the contrary, and that your abode there would not like you, though you were appointed thereunto; his Maieſtie deſired your ſeruice in thoſe parts, and you would perferre certaine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular affaires, to ſatisfie your owne pleaſures and inclinations, as if we were at the Romaines Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnals.</p>
            <p>You muſt grant mee this, that there are no examples for your proceedings, and that if in times paſt, there were rebels and diſobedient Subiects, they alwaies ſought to diſſemble, and to couer and hide their pretences with neceſſity: you vſe not any ſuch meanes, but are rather more hardned, &amp; ſeeme directly and openly to oppoſe your ſelfe againſt his Maieſtie: What puniſhment thinke you doth ſuch a crime deſerue? One fault willingly and moſt commonly draweth on another. What haue you done ſince you came from <hi>Metz?</hi> You haue borne away the Kings Mother, and carried her to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouliſme,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13800:11"/>where you ſpread the enſignes of reuolt, and there determine vpon warre, and the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the State? What audaciouſneſſe is this, and whatan enterpriſe haue you vndertaken, to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the intents of a good Mother, towards her deare Sonne; to trouble and ſet at variance the harmony and conſent of their wils; to ſhake, and as it were to breake the bond of nature, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to pull out of ſo great a Princes breſt, the loue which ſhe oweth to her Sonne, to her King, and to him that ſpecially loueth her? Miſerable man, (if I muſt needes vſe this tearme) what is your pretence? To ruinate his Maieſties affaires, and to ouerthrow and ſubuert the publique peace of the Land? It is the conceit of a franticke braine, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by the author of malice: Doe you not think and perſwade your ſelfe, that reaſon once taking place, but that the Queene will condemne your pernicious deſignes, and the proceedings that you haue cauſed her to vſe? there is no doubt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, your forces cannot altogether breake and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the principall motions of her ſuggeſtions, which are Nature and the feare of God, able and ſufficient to driue away the clouds and fictions wherewith you ſerue your turne: The common people, manifeſtly ſee it, and curſe you, as often as they behold and looke into the euils which you bring vpon them: They know that his Maieſtie is a moſt Chriſtian Prince, that he loueth his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfectly well, and that he neuer gaue any iuſt cauſe to procure this euaſion: They are aſſured
<pb facs="tcp:13800:11"/>and otherwiſe comforted, that this ſeparation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue long: Their mutuall deſire already is to ſee one another, and to ſhew the effects of their reciprocall loues: Expect not then to fortifie the weakeneſſe of your cauſe, by the detention of the Queenes perſon; you ſhall neuer haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of her heart and will, to the ruine of the State, and her owne glory.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, I muſt begin againe, and leade you to the execution of that which this burning feuer enduceth in your fantaſie. You haue diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayed, &amp; allienated (as you pretend) the Queenes intents, you muſt now blame the gouernement both within and without the Realme, and in all places proclaime warre, and the deſolation of your Countrey; wherein ſpecially your deſigne cannot take effect. Forraigne Princes honour, &amp; too much deſire the amity and alliance of our Monarch; they haue ſeene miracles, as it were, in his actions, and that in his young yeares, with a manly and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute generoſitie, he hath danted the monſters of his Realme, and by an admirable care and wiſedome, procured peace to thoſe that had warre; which is the cauſe, that by a generall conſent they giue him the glorious title of the <hi>Arbitrator of Chriſtendome;</hi> and his amity is ſo deſirable and profitable, that ſuch as are admitted thereunto (how farre diſtant ſoeuer they be) ſleepe and take their reſts, without any apprehenſion of trouble; how then will they vnderſtand your clamours, vnleſſe it be to blame and condemne them?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:12"/>
            <p>The peace that we enioy, is an euident teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the piety, iuſtice, and prouidence of our King; and therefore it is impoſſible that your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions ſhould deſtroy the truth, and that which we ſee with our owne eyes, in ſuch manner, that if in long time, there hath beene a happy raigne in <hi>France,</hi> it is now at this preſent, where all Orders and degrees are ſeene to flouriſh; Vertue therein is commended, and Pietie (the true ſupport of the State) particularly adored, where our King is as it were, a perfect modell; Eccleſiaſticall perſons are reuerenced, and called to counſell in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt important affaires, they enioy and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe their reuenewes without trouble; the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are loued and reſpected; Iuſtice is indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without feare executed; the Commons are not oppreſſed nor charged with Subſidies or new impoſitions; and all eſtates together, haue nothing ſo much in recommendation, nor ſo deare, as this good King, for whoſe health and proſperity they daily make their feruent prayers vnto God. How then ſhould they be moued to offence? and that to accommodate your humours, they ſhould ſet fire on their houſes, and ruinate and ſpoile one the other, after that to expect nothing elſe but miſery in this life, and damnation in the life to come?</p>
            <p>I know aſſuredly, that you ſpecially build your deſignes vpon the inconſtancy of the popularity, as if the conſideration of your perſon, or of any others, were of more importance vnto them, then
<pb facs="tcp:13800:12"/>the Kings, and their owne preſeruation: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are deceiued; the loue and obedience that they beare and owe vnto him, are by Gods owne finger ingrauen in their hearts, with a caracter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be defaced, and your name is execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the ſworne enemy of their good: they openly report and ſay, that it is impoſſible that he which is wicked &amp; cruell againſt his own children, ſhould euer be good to others; that he which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ruine &amp; ſubuerſion of his natiue Country, vnworthy of humaine ſociety: that the poyſon of your venemous heart hath long time appeared, and that it ought and ſhould be choaked in the birth; that the ſpots and vncleaneneſſe of your ſoule, and the counſels which your actions haue impoſed vpon it, makes you play the laſt act of your Tragedy. To conclude and be ſhort, they are willing to contribute and giue fire and fagot to conſume the author of ſo many miſchiefes. I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe all theſe circumſtances vnto you without flattery, to let you ſee the ſtate wherevnto your affaires are reduced.</p>
            <p>Tell me now, who hath brought you to theſe extreamities? Is it the diſcontentment of the Queene? ſhe had no other but that onely which you haue procured; and ſay that ſhe had, doth it belong to you to intermeddle with the difference that is between Princes? It is not like that of yours: The Sonne and the Mother would ſoone haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed together, and good endeauour would haue reduced all things to their true ends: Therein you
<pb facs="tcp:13800:13"/>are two-fold culpable; one by ſhewing your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill will; the other by ſeeking to ſet diuiſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Sonne and the Mother, the Subiect and the King, and a loue which could not be broken, but by the impiteous windes of your ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter counſels.</p>
            <p>It may be, ye will alleadge that you are none of his Maieſties priuie-Counſellours, and your honour is ſuch that you would know all, that you may enterpriſe much; let vs reaſon boldly: The counſell which the King now hath, is the ſame that his Father had, who by his valorous actions, and wiſe conduction, was called the <hi>wonder of Kings:</hi> That great King, made profit of mens actions, and perfectly vnderſtood the mindes of his ſubiects, and yet he neuer-made you priuie to the counſell of his moſt important affaires: He was content to doe you good, and to continue you in the Offices that you enioyed; muſt you then complaine, that the King his ſonne, and ſucceſſour in his vertues, followeth the ſame courſe and counſell, by the ayde and dexterity whereof, he had giuen vs a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall peace, and almoſt a golden world? Beleeue mee, rather praiſe and commend that good King, who in a manner had buried in obliuion the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of that which you know, and which I dare not touch, fearing to offend his indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: I leaue it to the regiſters of the Court of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it poſſible that you ſhould be diſcontented, that his <hi>Maieſty</hi> affecteth, and doth good to ſome
<pb facs="tcp:13800:13"/>one of his Seruitors, more then to you. I thinke you are not at that point; for what other ſhould that then be, but to ſhew your ſelfe vnthankefull for, and to condemne that which <hi>Henry</hi> the third did for you? He loued you moſt particularly, and gaue you all that you enioy, beſides 8000. Franks yearely reuenews. This your great fortune, was much enuyed, and many men ſpake thereof, to your preiudice, which reaſon denyed: I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ſome in reſpect of you ſaid, that men in Kings hands, are like vnto Counters which they make to value as much as they thinke good: And that there was neuer any Monarch, but that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome proofes of particular affections, which in truth are Royall actions, worthy of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. And it is no ſmall good, to a great Prince, to make a good choyſe of, and to haue faithfull ſeruitors about him, with ſecuritie and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity, to whom hee may diſcouer and diſcloſe his heart, and thoughts: Euery one of vs ſee it by experience, and finde nothing more pleaſing and acceptable, then to impart and vnfold our affaires vnto, and with thoſe whoſe affections and amities are well knowne vnto vs. Our King loueth with great iudgement, hee knoweth and will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the merit and fidelitie wherewith he hath bin ſerued; I meane, the more he (ſpecially) whom he loueth, hath amiable quallities and worthy the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of a King. I will not particularize them, nor proceed further in this ſubiect, only I will ſay, that we muſt hold all that for Law, which pleaſeth the
<pb facs="tcp:13800:14"/>Prince, and that for their ſake, we muſt loue thoſe whom they loue, much leſſe ought wee to enuye and hate them: It ſhould in truth be a moſt hard thing, and without all likelihood or apparance of reaſon for Subiects to impoſe lawes to their ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, and to maſter their pleaſures and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they themſelues being free in their owne particular houſes, to loue and to doe good to thoſe to whom they will; and I ſay further, that the fauour and fortune whereof wee ſpeake, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not that which is due vnto Princes, neither yet abateth any thing of the aduantage and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Nobilitie, nor vſeth any violence or euill entertainement towards others, whereby we may truly ſay, that no man can nor may diſlike or contradict it, but onely of meere enuy, the ſworne enimy of all good actions, and of the aduancement and greatneſſe of vertuous men.</p>
            <p>This is the Table or Portraiture which I thought good to ſet before your eyes, without diſſimulation, to let you ſee the greatneſſe of your faults, and the extreamity whereinto you are falne. It may be you will be grieued that I diſplay them ſo openly; I proteſt that I haue not ſet them all downe, and that without doing wrong to you, and to mine owne intent, I could not ſay leſſe. My pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is herein to ſet downe ſufficient to perſwade you to the truth, and to ſearch the wound to the bottome, to the end, that hauing any feeling, you your ſelfe may ſeeke how to heale it; you ſhould doe it while time ſerueth: This is the aduice which
<pb facs="tcp:13800:14"/>I will giue you. A Lampe goeth out if you put too much moyſture vnto it; acknowledge that your too great eſtate hath reduced you to this point of great loſſe, and not yours onely, but your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens, whom you cruelly drew into your rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Kings haue Iron armes; for Gods ſake ſtay not till our King lifts vp his, you will ſurely be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces with the blow; preuent it by humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, certainely his <hi>Mateſty</hi> is iuſt and benigne; hee puniſheth and exterminateth obſtinate Rebells, but he pardoneth thoſe that aske mercy and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe. It is the onely hauen wherein you ſhall finde hope of reliefe, refer your ſelfe with a good heart freely vnto his bounty, and you ſhall not be deceiued in your expectation.</p>
            <p>Suffer the Queene to be at libertie to revnite and ioyne her affections with her Sonnes; let your children be ſuerties and pledges of your libertie, let them fall downe at his <hi>Maieſties</hi> feete, to proteſt and warrant your amendment, and your moſt humble ſubmiſſions to full fill all obedience in time to come: Diſcharge your Souldiers, and let euery place ſound the praiſe of ſo compleat a Prince, and your reſolution to die in his ſeruice. I am with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt perſwaded, that this proceeding will be acceptable vnto him, and that following the example of <hi>Henry</hi> the great, his father, he will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and preſerue you. What glory (my Lord) will it be vnto you to haue appeaſed the wrath of ſo puiſſant a Prince? To haue of your ſelfe reob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his fauour? To haue pacified the tumult
<pb facs="tcp:13800:15"/>which you had raiſed in his Realme? To haue procured peace to your owne ſoule, and reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your lateſt daies, and to haue reeſtabliſhed the ſtate and fortunes of your Children. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God gine you grace earneſtly to thinke vpon theſe things, and to put them in effect: I deſire and wiſh it more then any other, that I may ſee you reſtored, and haue the meanes hereafter to ſay, as I haue hether done that I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt affectioned ſeruant, <hi>L: S.</hi> D.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Paris</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> March, 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13800:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
